like there were mostly something for me
to do like okay this needs improve my
listening Superman like at the moment my
hold on
sensuality can like improve by by me
being quite established in it like or
other like you know being
they come home restraining another
restraining even though it comes with
torts hmm and okay I can do this until
I'm like you know it's it's where I'm
very steady in it in this I see certain
evil oh I was at the invitation
irritations thoughts of cruelty sort of
like finding false different things
different people those things I can
improve on but it's just that I'm um
like finding less and less sort of
directions for me to what am I gonna do
next sort of thing
well you you're asking what you're gonna
do next
when you haven't even completed when
you're supposed to do now so what you
should have next is be patient as in
what you should do right now and next
and next and next if you're trying to
figure out what to do next
while you still know these things can be
improved on why why would you do that
why would you accept that thought in
that line of reasoning
like you might wonder well why would I
do next but that's obviously not the
issue here
no it's frustration so well exactly
which means oh so now you're wondering
what to do next well in reality the only
reason you're wondering what to do next
is because you still haven't done what
you're supposed to do now so you're
frustrated we did say all you want to
just have it the next step as well in
the meantime and it doesn't work like
that so even if you were to figure out
what to do next
you won't be what to do next it would be
simply to appease that frustration or
lack of patience so then the question is
why are you impatient why is sitting
sitting without doing anything why is
that unpleasant
while you're looking past it while
you're not seeing it as something oh
wait a minute like you know oh this is
what I can improve on this working dude
oh yeah that's all fine well what do I
do next then oh wait what do you even do
before I improve on these things which
is why I find it unpleasant to sit alone
and not have anything to do why is it an
issue so what you do next is basically
what you need to do first not forget
your situation
because yeah I mean your thoughts of
sensuality or restraining that because
that's what situation is at a time when
your thoughts of closed area will you're
restraining that because that's what
situation is at a time but then when you
have thoughts of neither sensuality no
cruelty but kind of you know pressure of
boredom or lack of activity or something
unpleasant oh then you find something to
do instead of dealing with that well
right what am i doing to deal with that
well that's the thing if you you
shouldn't basically be doing anything to
do with it you should be learning how to
endure the neutral feeling because it's
not unpleasant the only reason you're
feeling is a pleasant is because you
keep refusing to acknowledge it that's
the whole point
seeming like the pain of boredom even
anxiety fear of boredom it's only so
cause you're refusing to acknowledge it
because you're looking past it
that's very much where the issue is um
well yeah sort of pressured I'm not
doing anything I'm just sitting I'll
brush it but what do I do next it's a
thought that I shouldn't really
entertain well it's a thought yeah yeah pretty
well it's a thought yeah yeah pretty
much
it's a thought that you will have to
arise because you've been counted the
whole life revolves around figuring out
what to do next
either what centrality to pursue next
what distraction to pursue next what
problem to avoid next that's what
people's life is that's what they always
need that activity to kind of enable
them to keep floating that's why
everybody is afraid of Solitude that's
why we say you need to learn how to find
pleasure in solitude when there is
nothing to do like that so until that
happens you will have thoughts of what
we'll do next but you also same like
with sensuality you have an option
whether it's entertain disclose open you
that state of what we do next without
giving in to define marital next because
what I do next is indeed the thoughts of
what do I do next
that's what you do right now and next
same principle just staring are two
different things
does end I sometimes like oh maybe I
should try to establish the body thumb
that really like should I do that
try to do that cuz you know I'm trying
to find an answer to this could that
like even if I do end up doing that this
is it wholesome for me to pursue that to
get to that stage well again as you said
before it's not about what you should do
it's about what you won't do what I do
next is a state of mind state of
uncertainty you can act out of craving
and try to get rid of that state of
uncertainty by providing answer what you
should do next
you cannot get out of craving so if you
wonder what should you do next you
realize well I don't doesn't matter what
I will do I know what I will not do so
that's what you should do don't do
anything they would be along the lines
of things you shouldn't be doing and
then so what do I do next I do that I
endure the question of what do I do next
this is basically the practice is just
you have to constantly keep undermining
that tendency to have things on your own
terms to put yourself first and then
what do I do now this I do what this I
don't do you're undermining that by not
giving in to finding that answer but by
enduring it yeah but what do i do what
do i do so that's how that state of
uncertainty is unpleasant but again it's
unpleasant only because you don't want
it in itself it's not the pleasant or
unpleasant mingi this isolates this failed state of
mingi this isolates this failed state of
confusion like you're exactly stable
confusion is real as such for as long as
you keep trying to replace it with a
state of non confusion you're ignoring
the nature of the phenomenon as such
which means you you practice your
efforts are then aimed at changing the
content of that state not then not
understanding the nature because it's
very clear that you are in the state of
confusion there's nothing ambiguous
about that so I didn't need to keep
trying to define it state the confusion
confuse me he knows confused mind as
confused mind non confused mind as non
confused mind so well he replaces
confused mind with a non confused mind
that means he doesn't know either it's
basically going beyond up that's without
his state of confusion what is it how
and if you keep giving in to seeking the
answer of that you're overlooking that
it is very clear as such doubt is clear
in itself as a doubt so you kick in
doubt this you can doubt that but you
cannot doubt that you're experiencing
doubt so that's the level now you need
to train towards a state of confusion is
here okay so the confused mind is
present enduring doesn't matter what you
are confused about you know what you
will not do so that's not an issue
there's nothing there to talk about you
just need to uphold that and now in
terms of so what do then I do on top of
things I don't do well that's something
I've turned you off and you realize oh
that's what I have to do but you can't
do that on your own terms that's what
can ever become the answer what do I do
I undo that like that you can even think
that but we actually start enduring it
he cannot be done on your own terms as
something you do which is why it never
provides the answer that you seek but
that's why it undermines that dependence
on the answer you seek but the whole
point of practice is to endure the right
things anybody can endure anything but not
anybody can endure anything but not
anybody can in do the right things that
need to be endured that's what most
people I mean we have insane amount of
determination and commitment and still
have completely wrong views because
they're not enduring the right things
yes that's that's that's pretty much
other side of the coin is like well
again whatever question present itself
don't look at the content don't look at
the answer how do I know am i doing the
right thing what is the experience of
that oh it's a state of confusion hey we
just spoke about now that's the whole
point certain questions will present
certain questions will present
themselves you must answer this but you
know it's fine yeah okay okay we'll give
you that all the previous question
that's fine but this is the one you must
actually it's still a question it's
still the same nature it's still the
phenomenon of confusion the mind of
confusion oh so that's I will not answer it
and to degree it makes sense that I
cannot make confusion I provide clarity
out of exactly I mean you you can only
act out of trying to get rid of that
state which means you're not doing
anything in terms of understanding or
overcoming the unpleasantness of that
state you're only replacing it which
means you still remain equally liable to
it other people keep kind of habitually
acting out of doubt trying to get rid of
the doubt the unpleasantness only by
finding the answer very clarifying the
answer by revisiting the answer by
rehashing the whole thing that they
already know they can never please that
because it's not it's not rational it's
not about providing the answer which you
already have it's about removing that
emotional discomfort and that's not in
your rational control so you just sort
of you know squirming and twisting and
turning until it hopefully disappears
and then the more you do it the more you
the more dependent you become in doing
it which means what used to provide the
answer won't be enough
after a while nothing like
okay thank you even when you say that
it's it's not about what you do what you
don't do I know that's pretty much a
decent answer back up pretty much for me
is it it appears to be a decent answer
but then it's nothing more friendly
satisfactory but and that's that's
that's that's one thing that you you're
kind of learning through making effort
is to not trust the emotional
satisfaction or dissatisfaction as a
criteria for what makes sense or not
everybody starts like that basically
what pleases you that's what seems to be
right what displeases you that's why you
take to be wrong but there is no other
criteria that which means you're judging
things as right or wrong simply based on
how they make you feel and you don't
want that and that's the whole point if
if people could effortlessly judge right
is Right wrong is wrong regardless of
how it makes them feel they would
effortlessly fall into the right view so
it's not an SI incidental that you have
to endure the pain and discomfort and
seeming confusion in regard to what you
kind of know it's right but you cannot
accept because it's so displeasing if
you injured through that the displeasure
will fade away and then you realize no
this is right I always knew this was
right I just had to go through it and
endure it and that's why that's where
the review is that's going beyond the
doubt you don't go beyond the doubt by
satisfying every possible answer you can
doubt them and be confused about you go
beyond the doubt by being unable anymore
to resist the discomfort of God like you
became stronger than it doesn't matter
the amount of doubt the martyr
discomfort cannot waver your mind in
regard to the nature of it you can still
doubt the content and sometimes even
clarify it needs to be clarified but you
won't have that burden if I must do that
because I don't know any other
escaped from this yes
only reason that I do anything else is
because it provides an idea of certainty
like yeah and that's inevitable way of
starting your practice yeah but sooner
or later is gonna lead you to dead end
so then you can either you know dig up a
new inspiration toward something would
change the tradition or change the
monastery or change the teacher as
people do when they practice arounds
drive or eventually disrobe or you can
they realize but it's not about
inspiration it's not about having
something to do it's it's about not
depending on anything that can be done
that's how you free yourself from karma
not by doing it but by understanding
beyond it
would you mean be like an inspiration in
this instance regular well it like
seemed like you you recognized the
problem as you sell it for example
sensuality hmm to you oh I can work on
this yeah that's fine and you work on it
but see that was initially probably
enough to keep you with it within the
context of practice but then a few days
later or what do I do next
while I still work on the are you free
from sensuality so you ask what to the
next no yet here you are asking what to
do next
well where's they routed routed
basically in dependence on certain
extent or inspiration that now has run
dry because you've been repeating the
same practice of not giving in to
sensuality so it doesn't you don't get
that same inspirational buzz from it so
to speak so now he cook you need to find
something more what do we do next
while I still do this exactly it's very
unpleasant to practice without
inspiration and that's exactly where the
practice is because if you start
practice you know that then even on the
most uninspiring days of your life you
cannot go back you cannot like slip back
you cannot do things that you would
regret later because you stopped acting
out of high feel but the only way to
stop acting wanna kind of how you feel
is to go through not acting on how to
how you feel to endure it
because nothing has changed the thoughts
you had when you inspire will not you
know very strange sensual thoughts that
idea practice context hasn't changed
what has changed is how you feel about
it
the novelty right now the inspiration or
not so is that oh so now I'm looking for
what else do I do
on account of basically my feelings
changing not only kind of always
completing what I had to do or whatever
else you're just acting in a kind of how
I feel trying to avoid the discomfort
and that's also kind of ties in with
what we spoke before while back
Vicki my or what do i do what do i what
should I do what you do without
realizing you're only doing lots of
stuff you're already sitting on the
chair walking on the meditation path I
don't know feeding a cat you're already
doing oh the body is already performing
all these things and you completely
unaware of it because the only doing the
to recognize is doing on the terms of my
own self I do this I do that failing to
see that it's doing happening already
and only the only thing even when
yourself does something is basically you
yourself can only appropriate that which
body does already what the body can do
already it's only appropriate action
would come under as intention I don't
know the thing is that say the other day
I was lying down and I have habit of
wiggling my foot and I am Boogaloo my
foot I don't see any intention of me
doing that but I'm doing so but I also
my missing sort of well no there other
thing there are those things that you're
doing kind of sub intentionally so to
speak and those things are not things
you necessarily need to worry about it's
the intention determines where the thing
is going to be wholesome or unwholesome
if there is no intention there's an
action something you know actually you
should worry about but when you
intentionally choose to I don't know
we're good afoot because he provides you
with physical pleasure let's say oh
that's a completely different intention
of completely different action because
it's rooted in completely four things
it's the same thing externally but
that's not what determines whether
action is is wholesome or on house
it's whether it's rooted in wholesome or
unwholesome internally
my responsibility toward sensuality is
whenever I see a sensual thought not to
be involved it not like restrain myself
from it
yeah restrained from welcoming it
delighting in it thinking more on
account of it towards it letting it
basically fester you cannot prevent them
from arising yeah but you can prevent
them from staying by not entertaining
them underlying tendencies or whatever
it's it's it's not really my
responsibility yeah they're indirect
responsibilities see you know that
you're not free from sensuality so you
know that simply by welcoming central
thoughts because you're not free from
sensuality by welcoming them sensuality
will increase underlying tendencies will
increase so you know that indirectly by
accepting this I am actually resulting
in increasing the the underlying
tendency to increase which means it's
going to be coming more and more often
then just because I'm restraining I
cannot expect them to dry out you can't
expect them to dry out but you don't
know when they will dry out yeah you
will you can know that while I'm not
entertaining it thus if I'm not
entertaining it I am NOT fueling
whatever underlying tendency there are
which means simply by not entertaining
you are drawing them up and you can know
that for sure it's just that people like
usually want more they want to know how
long I have to do this and you can't
know that and that's the simile in the
suit of the eye the axe handle the
carpenter uses his his axe every day and
the handle is wearing thin but he
doesn't know how much it's wearing thin
but he keeps using it he doesn't care
how much it's wear anything he's using
the handle and then whatever few years
later he comes in realizes oh I have to
replace my handle now it's way too thin
it's unusable gone faded away
yeah don't think of the practice in
general but in this particular instance
I think of oh I will do this and then to
achieve like a certain goal like freedom
from sensuality I will restrain my
thoughts and then I will achieve the
freedom from sensuality you should think
of it more like I will restrain my
thoughts and that's my goal basically to
develop a type like a state of being
that is about restraint of central
thoughts not about indulgence of sensual
thoughts so that's your goal that sense
restraint becomes your known not all the
way around that sense restraint becomes
effortless not other way around and if
that becomes your goal which means if
there becomes you goal it will be
impossible to not have your efforts
directed towards that goal so if there
becomes you go with all of your invested
effort it would be impossible to not be
free from centrality
in certain ways that became the gold and
the inspiration start growing our
websites yeah well like when what
happens is when when that becomes your
goal to be free from sensuality well
basically that goal is on the basis of
sensuality it's on the basis of craving
so you start like that but you want to
refine it further than the recognize
that well can you have freedom from
sensuality without sense restraint
impossible can you be free from
sensuality yet not be sense restraint
impossible so sense restraint needs to
be there either way so why don't I make
sense restrain my goal regardless of
whether I'm free from society or not
sense restraint will be my mode of being
for the rest of my life and then you'll
be free from suggesting if you stick to
that it's again it's like the other
simile the Buddha said the hand lies on
her eggs
so whether she wants whether she wishes
the chicks pierce out safely and come
into this world healthy and alive or
whether she doesn't wish that they will
if she lays on her eggs if she makes the
effort but if she gets too busy figuring
out what will she do with the chicks
when they come out and how much she'll
enjoy them and look after them she
forgets to sit on the eggs they won't
come up even if she has all the
inspiration determination for them to
come out they won't because she's not
doing creating the necessary basis for
it so it doesn't mean you start by
wanting your chicks but then you realize
okay so how would that come to be so you
start by wanting to be free from
underlying tendency toward sensuality
but then you refine it further and see
how would that come to be well that
would have to come to be through the
sense restraint
so that's my goal now because for you
from where you are at sensory strength
equals freedom from underlying tendency
prevention of underlying tendency drying
up of sensuality and if there is
anything more within that you need to do
it will be done again only within sensor
strain that you have to do not in place
of or instead of which means you just
have to start doing the sensor straight
and then if there is anything more it
will show itself through what your order
you doing
so go same for like ill will you make
your goal to become like a steady state
of being that's based on non ill-will
regardless of what's in front of you
what thoughts present themselves
thoughts of ill-will thoughts of hatred
you don't welcome
you don't cherish you don't delight and
you don't entertain it that's your call
you don't have to worry about what's
gonna come as a result of it because you
already know what will come as a result
of it you already know that as long as
you lay on the eggs chicks will have to
roost they will have to come out even if
you don't think about it you just don't
need to think about
as a belief they're already like it's
not even a belief you ordered the
recognizer on some level that sense
restraint implies non-centrality create
absence of sensuality you don't know to
what extent but you already see the
thread you already see the connection
we'll be see trying to figure it out
that it sort of that's sort of too
little to acknowledge like they're
saving again like what would you just
said let them that I already know a
certain yeah it's too little to
acknowledge exactly you need more but
the only reason you need more is cuz
you've been craving for more if you can
do that craving you realize I don't need
anything thus doesn't matter how subtle it is
thus doesn't matter how subtle it is
it's more than enough that's when you
basically stop needing an inspiration
for practice that's when you become that
practice you don't need to be doing
for that state of confusion has run out
of his course yeah you might be confused
in regard to certain content Oh or
certain choices or what to do here what
today but you will not be confusing
regard to the nature in regards to do
you order of things the order of thing
is you need to lay on the eggs for
chicks to roost there is absolutely no
other way there that's just how it works
yet here you are knowing that ignoring
that and worrying what school will you
send your chicks into and what will they
wear and what will they do and how will
you teach them this and then at the
expense of that you're forgetting that
you need to sit on the eggs because now
you'll get all confused of what they do
so you stop being confused even about
watching you could you've been giving in
to trying to get rid of the confusion
failing to see what doesn't matter how
confused I am about how will I raise my
chicks I cannot be confused about the
nature of that being present there
chicks will come as a result of laying
in the eggs sensuality cannot manifest
if I mold my being into the sense
restraint not other way around then Bob
will I do next I figure out when that
comes in the meantime I know what I will
not do